<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Marcus Aurelius</title>
<link>https://www.marcus.limo/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.marcus.limo/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Meditations of a Pragmatic Philosopher</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Methodology Lifecycle Governance for Environmental Assets</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/methodology-lifecycle/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Carbon credits quantify the greenhouse gas (GHG) emission reductions or removals achieved by projects or programs around the world that mitigate climate change. Carbon credit standards set rules and requirements to ensure the quality and integrity of these credits. Standards provide methodologies for measuring, monitoring and verifying the GHG benefits of different types of activities, such as renewable energy, forest conservation, or waste management.</p>
<p>In this post, I explore how existing carbon credit standards develop and maintain methodologies, as well as how decentralized governance mechanisms can facilitate destruction of credits from deprecated methodologies - leading to a more robust carbon market, better equipped to adapt to evolving scientific consensus.</p>
<section id="what-is-a-methodology-anyway" class="level1">
<h1>What is a Methodology Anyway?</h1>
<p>Much like a lab experiment you might have done in grade-school science class, a methodology specifies a detailed set of steps and procedures to reproduce a particular result.</p>
<p>A carbon credit methodology will typically specify: - the <strong>applicability conditions</strong> under which the activity should take place - how to define the <strong>boundaries</strong> of a project - how to construct an appropriate <strong>baseline</strong> (i.e.&nbsp;demonstrate that the project activities actually make a difference relative to the status quo) - how to <strong>quantify the greenhouse gas emissions</strong> avoided or removed by the activity - how to <strong>monitor</strong> the project to ensure the intended results are realized</p>
</section>
<section id="status-quo-methodology-development" class="level1">
<h1>Status Quo Methodology Development</h1>
<p>The first verified carbon credit system, the <a href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-kyoto-protocol/mechanisms-under-the-kyoto-protocol/the-clean-development-mechanism">Clean Development Mechanism</a>, was created 30 years ago under the Kyoto Protocol. Since then, the governance mechanisms for carbon credit standards have not changed much. In particular, they tend to favor opaque submission and review processes where most activities are carried out by permissioned insiders (e.g.&nbsp;staff at the standards body). While standards typically feature a public comment period in their methodology development process, the submitted comments are not published in full, and it is difficult to tell if issues that were raised have been properly addressed.</p>
<section id="example-verras-verified-carbon-standard-vcs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example-verras-verified-carbon-standard-vcs">Example: Verra’s Verified Carbon Standard (VCS)</h2>
<p><a href="https://verra.org/">Verra</a> is a non-profit organization that manages several standards and programs for climate action and sustainable development, including the VCS Program, which is the world’s most widely used GHG crediting program. The VCS Program has issued over one billion carbon credits from thousands of projects in 80 countries.</p>
<p>The VCS Program has its own methodologies that have been approved for use by Verra, as well as methodologies from other approved GHG programs, such as the Clean Development Mechanism (CDM) and the Climate Action Reserve (CAR). All methodologies undergo a <a href="https://verra.org/methodologies-main/develop-a-methodology/">review and consultation process</a> to ensure they meet the rules and requirements of the VCS Program.</p>
<p>Verra periodically reviews VCS methodologies to ensure they continue to reflect best practices, scientific consensus, and evolving market conditions and technical developments in a sector.</p>
<p>However, there is no standardized mechanism in the methodology governance process for deprecating an approved methodology if/when it reaches end-of-life - though, as we’ll see, several methodologies have been “phased out” ad hoc over the years.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="cleaning-up-a-decade-old-mess" class="level1">
<h1>Cleaning Up a Decade-Old Mess</h1>
<p>During the joint launch of <a href="https://docs.toucan.earth/toucan/bridge/carbon-bridge">Toucan’s one-way carbon bridge</a> and <a href="https://klimadao.finance">KlimaDAO</a>, about 700,000 tonnes of carbon credits were bridged from the Verra registry issued under the AM0001 methodology for decomposition of HFC-23 (a byproduct from production of refrigerant).</p>
<p>This particular <a href="https://cdm.unfccc.int/methodologies/DB/GAOZAY2DWIQHK71LJS027N6N4AV6SC">methodology was originally developed under the CDM</a>, and was carried forward into Verra’s VCS. However, in the wake of the Montreal Protocol, which established mandatory commitments at the national level for preventing emissions of hydroflourocarbons like HFC-23, Verra subsequently <a href="https://verra.org/phasing-out-hfc-23-projects/">ceased issuance of credits under any methodology related to HFC-23</a>.</p>
<p>The HFC-23 methodology was also called into question because of concerns that some project developers were <a href="https://carbonbetter.com/story/additionality/">producing more refrigerant than they actually had buyers for, simply to issue carbon credits based on the decomposition of the HFC-23 byproduct</a>.</p>
<p>After the methodology was discontinued by Verra, no steps were taken to address the millions of tonnes of credits which were issued under this methodology and remained on the books of many carbon market participants. This created ambiguity around the value of these assets, and led many in the carbon markets to conveniently forget about their existence. Nonetheless, for years after the deprecation of the methodology, transactions and retirements continued in the shadows of the over-the-counter (OTC) market.</p>
<section id="leveraging-public-governance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leveraging-public-governance">Leveraging Public Governance</h2>
<p>This is a clear coordination failure: no new credits would be issued under the methodology, yet there was no mechanism to signal that the market had moved on from the existing credits and destroy them once and for all to prevent further use.</p>
<p>Of course, Verra did not originate this methodology - it was originally developed under the CDM - but it did continue to allow retirement of these credits after ceasing issuance. Under its current Terms of Use, Verra lacks the ability to unilaterally destroy properly issued credits held by registry users, and registry users have no incentive to destroy their own assets.</p>
<p>As the situation became clear to the KlimaDAO community, Toucan implemented a restriction on the BCT pool to prevent more HFC-23 credits from being added to the pool. However, just like the off-chain market, the Digital Carbon Market had now inherited a significant chunk of these credits.</p>
</section>
<section id="sorting-the-laundry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sorting-the-laundry">Sorting the Laundry</h2>
<p>Seeing this as an opportunity to exercise the unique advantages of KlimaDAO’s public governance mechanism, I helped conduct an investigation into the history and activity of these credits.</p>
<p>On one hand, <a href="https://www.rff.org/publications/working-papers/the-net-emissions-impact-of-hfc-23-offset-projects-from-the-clean-development-mechanism/">academic research</a> indicated that some HFC-23 decomposition projects had been properly implemented, potentially even under-crediting - while other projects had engaged in deliberate over-creditng by producing more refrigerant than they would under a Business-As-Usual (BAU) scenario.</p>
<p>However, based on the Verra <a href="https://registry.verra.org/app/search/VCS/VCUs">public registry data</a> on retirements, I found that credits from I found that this methodology had not been used for retirement in about 2 years.</p>
<p>As such, the path forward was clear to me: even if the particular project whose credits ended up in the KlimaDAO treasury were from a project that did not abuse the system, and issued at a time when the methodology was still actively used for retirement, those credits were objectively no longer being used, and therefore did not warrant going inclusion in the digital carbon market.</p>
<p>So I began to prepare a <a href="https://forum.klimadao.finance/d/115-kip-26a-hfc-23-cleanup-operation-with-additional-background">governance proposal</a> which would destroy all of the HFC-23 credits in the BCT pool. I also approached Toucan for assistance in the process, both in terms of capital to destroy the credits and a special function to allow burning of credits from the pool without paying the selective redemption fee.</p>
<p>Several weeks later, <a href="https://snapshot.org/#/klimadao.eth/proposal/0x2ae3fce131f98bf22ec9ef306a13e359002eaea0d111328149204dfd9dc9b2e4">KLIMA token holders voted definitively to destroy the HFC-23 credits</a>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="murphys-law-for-methodologies" class="level1">
<h1>Murphy’s Law for Methodologies</h1>
<p>Based on this experience I propose a corollary of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murphy's_law">Murphy’s Law</a> for carbon credit methodologies:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>No methodology is perfect - therefore all methodologies will be criticized.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Criticism and scrutiny is absolutely essential to progress this market and develop the most effective and impactful methodologies. But when that data-driven, scientific criticism is wrapped up into an overly simplistic narrative and shouted from the rootops, it can disrupt the market.</p>
<p>Rather than abandoning a methodology wholesale based on simplistic narratives, the carbon market needs mechanisms to deliberately evolve over time. The goal should be to avoid disrupting project developers midflight, and prevent an inefficient race to the top of the price curve, which distorts the relationship between price, cost and efficiency.</p>
<p>KlimaDAO established a precedent to maintain support for a given methodology until market participants have not utilized that asset for retirement purposes in years. As new supply comes online and KlimaDAO integrates that supply into its ecosystem and treasury, the HFC-23 situation provides an example of progressively improving the carbon markets using public governance.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflecting-on-the-hfc-23-situation" class="level1">
<h1>Reflecting on the HFC-23 situation</h1>
<p>In a perfect world, could the KlimaDAO and Toucan teams have known about the HFC-23 credits and designed the BCT pool criteria to prevent them from entering in the first place? Sure. But would this have prevented criticism of other methodologies? Certainly not.</p>
<p>Whether the methodology is HFC-23 decomposition or renewable energy based credits, REDD+ avoided deforestation or improved cookstoves, all methodologies should and will be subject to criticism so they can improve over time. This is a feature of the open, public nature of environmental assets - not a bug.</p>
<p>However, there is a bug in our social infrastructure: careful, data-driven scientific criticism is undermined by academia’s “publish or perish” incentive structure, leading to click-baity journal titles like <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/368760959_Cooking_the_books_Pervasive_over-crediting_from_cookstoves_offset_methodologies">“Cooking the books”</a>. These articles are then blindly picked up by media outlets, which have an incentive to generate impressions rather than foster nuanced understanding.</p>
<p>In this case of this cookstoves article, the authors misleadingly emphasize the overcrediting associated with the oldest CDM cookstove methodology, which very few new projects are deploying, while their detailed analysis indicates that some of the new cookstove methodologies may actually be issuing <em>fewer</em> credits than tonnes of carbon dioxide actually avoided. Instead of emphasizing that methodologies in this high-impact sector have gradually improved over time, the authors emphasize problems with the oldest version of this methodology.</p>
<p>This dynamic places project developers, the people on the ground doing the work, in a very precarious position: raising capital to take on a multi-year project, while having to constantly worry that the next media takedown will be about the methodology they have adopted. It also leads to hesitation among the end users who retire carbon credits, since they can never be sure when the projects they choose to support will be called into question.</p>
<p>This counterproductive dynamic is a problem of incentive alignment. Public governance mechanisms for environmental markets, such as that pioneered by KlimaDAO in the Digital Carbon Market, can align the incentives of diverse market actors. There is an opportunity to build more robust mechanisms for governing the lifecyle of methodologies, which will ensure the market can move on from particular methodologies through a more deliberate and decisive process.</p>
</section>
<section id="signs-of-life" class="level1">
<h1>Signs of Life</h1>
<p>As evidence of the need for an end-of-life governance mechanism, several <a href="https://www.qcintel.com/carbon/article/us-hfc-and-southeast-asian-redd-credits-trade-15918.html">transactions of HFC-23 decomposition credits</a> were recently observed once again. Despite the long controversy, with arguments for and against going back and forth for over a decade, the market has not moved on from this methodology.</p>
<p>Since April of 2023, almost 30,000 tonnes of credits from an HFC-23 project have been retired in the Verra registry: [./recent-hfc23-retirements.png]</p>
<p>While these credits are from one of the projects which operated in good faith and did not abuse the system to overissue credits, the fact remains that this methodology has been subjected to extensive criticism, and yet no mechanism was deployed by the incumbent VCM participants to exclude the existing credits issued under this methodology from the market - unlike the DCM, which has used public governance to remove these credits from the market.</p>
</section>
<section id="setting-a-floor" class="level1">
<h1>Setting a Floor?</h1>
<p>There is much fanfare over the recent release of the Core Carbon Principles (CCPs) from the Integrity Council for the Voluntary Carbon Market. The hope is that this initiative will establish a clear floor for what defines a “high quality” carbon project. The ICVCM has only <a href="https://twitter.com/ic_vcm/status/1686015987269742592">just begun accepting applications on August 1st, 2023</a> for CCP labeling, with the first labels <a href="https://twitter.com/ic_vcm/status/1686015987269742592">expected to be given out by end of year</a>. It remains to be seen how the implementation of these unobjectionable, broadly accepted principles will be interpreted by the market, and by the media.</p>
<p>But if Murphy’s Law for Methodologies holds, then there will in future be specific issues raised through the normal process of scientific inquiry and consensus forming that undermines the integrity of a particular methodology. And so the CCPs themselves will need a mechanism for evolving over time to reflect that latest scientific consensus, which means they will likely need a mechanism for revoking a CCP label - an analogous problem to methodology deprecation as explored here.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-role-of-public-governance" class="level1">
<h1>The Role of Public Governance</h1>
<p>Unlike the methodology approval or CCP label application process, it is critical that the end-of-life process for methodologies is public. Various stakeholders, from end-users to traders to project developers and carbon experts, must align their incentives through a deliberate governance process to help the market move on. The mud-slinging which has characterized discussions around specific methodologies to date undermines public confidence in the fundamental premise of environmental markets, which doesn’t help any of the market participants, nor does it lead to scalable, high-integrity climate action.</p>
<p>Token-based governance, as used by KlimaDAO’s community to destroy the HFC-23 credits present in the DCM, is by no means perfect. There are a variety of problems to be solved, such as mitigating the role of whales and increasing community engagement, but it does demonstrates what is possible when incentives are aligned.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>governance</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/methodology-lifecycle/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/methodology-lifecycle/landscape.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scaling Climate Action with Blockchain Technology @ EthCC 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/ethcc-23/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YeSn_-aWfCc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>EthCC is one of the largest annual Ethereum conferences, and it was a joy to be back in Paris again to share the latest developments in the Digital Carbon Market.</p>
<p>I spoke toward the end of a set of a back-to-back talks from different projects applying blockchain to carbon markets. Many of the speakers before me had broad sweeping presentations, attempting to communicate a massive amount of information using dense slides and broad sweeping narratives. This led someone in the audience to ask the same question at the end of each talk: “What have you actually delivered to date?”</p>
<p>Having learned the perils of dense, text-heavy slides from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Unzc731iCUY">this excellent talk about how to speak</a>, I made sure my slides had the minimum text necessary, and I emphasized just a few key takeaways. Thankfully KlimaDAO has plenty of live, production systems to highlight, and I’ve explained the basics of carbon markets so often that I was able to keep my messaging very simple.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/ethcc-23/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/ethcc-23/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="73" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bootstrapping Impact Markets @ ETHPrague 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/eth-prague-23/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=84mcr0M_a7g" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>It was a joy to visit the beautiful city of Prague and speak at the historic <a href="https://www.paralelnipolis.cz/en/o-nas/en/">Paralelni Polis</a>. ETHPrague brought together some of the sharpest minds in Ethereum, open-source software and distributed computing, alongside solarpunks and the ReFi community.</p>
<p>There is growing excitement about new environmental assets that fund impact “beyond just carbon.” However, after about 30 years since the first voluntary carbon market, <a href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-kyoto-protocol/mechanisms-under-the-kyoto-protocol/the-clean-development-mechanism">the Clean Development Mechanism (CDM), was created under the Kyoto Protocol</a>, carbon markets themselves are still quite immature, and there are plenty of lessons to learn from their development thus far.</p>
<p>In this talk, I go over the basic structure of impact markets, discuss how carbon markets implement that structure, and some insights about how to bootstrap new impact markets.</p>
<p>I specifically highlight the tension between liquidity and fungibility for building scalable markets. Since a given environmental project will only create a certain number of impact certficates, the number of comparable assets may be quite small, which limits liquidity.</p>
<p>However, deep liquidity is necessary to support sophisticated financial instruments (e.g.&nbsp;forward funding, insurance). Given the high up-front funding requirements for environmental impact projects, spot liquidity is critical to ensure project developers and financiers have reliable prices to discount against.</p>
<p>I also highlight the ongoing work at KlimaDAO to bootstrap new strata in the digital carbon market by forward funding carbon projects using treasury capital, then once those credits are delivered, deploying a new liquidity pool that prices that type of project. For instance, KlimaDAO funded a <a href="https://forum.klimadao.finance/d/139-kip-32-starcb-eeimp-project/8">cookstove project in a refugee camp in Bangladesh</a> under the Gold Standard, and a <a href="https://forum.klimadao.finance/d/202-kip-34-aither-arbo-eligible-carbon-project-opportunity/11">forestry project in Africa</a> under Verra’s Verified Carbon Standard. Upon delivery, proposals will be advanced to use these credits to create a spot liquidity pool for the EEIMP (small scale energy efficiency) and ARBO (afforestation and reforestation) carbon pools proposed by KlimaDAO’s bridging partner C3.</p>
<p>These new liquidity pools will then provide real-time pricing data for spot credits of those types, so that financiers and project developers can negotiate forward funding for new, similar carbon projects on a level playing field. Project developers will also be able to access liquidity immediately upon delivery, rather than waiting to offload their credits to a buyer.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/eth-prague-23/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/eth-prague-23/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="72" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NYU Sustainable Travel &amp; Tourism Seminar: Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/nyu-ttrc-seminar/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vLpzU7W6OOY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>KlimaDAO was recently invited to attend and present at the second Sustainable Travel &amp; Tourism Seminar organized by the <a href="https://sites.google.com/nyu.edu/ttrc">NYU Travel &amp; Tourism Research Collaboratory</a>. The theme of this seminar was “Sustainability Monitoring and Evaluation” - over two days, we heard from a variety of individuals and organizations working to bring more sustainable practices to the travel &amp; tourism sector, and I shared some of the solutions KlimaDAO is working on to compensate for the emissions from aviation and live events in an efficient and transparent manner.</p>
<p>In my talk, I highlight the difficulty in verifying corporate social responsibility claims using antiquated manual retirement processes and PDF certificates, and demonstrate the increased transparency and improved user experience afforded by digital carbon credit retirement (powered by blockchain technology under the hood). I also compare a traditional aviation offset provider currently used by Air Canada (<a href="https://www.chooose.today/">Chooose</a>) with the automated retirement solution we are prototyping with <a href="https://www.klimadao.finance/blog/klimadao-and-fly-air-launch-automated-carbon-offsetting-for-chartered-jets">FlyAir</a>, a private jet booking company.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/nyu-ttrc-seminar/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/nyu-ttrc-seminar/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Toward an Open Data Standard for Environmental Assets @ Sustainable Blockchain Summit 2023 in Boston</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-boston/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2GHNhknh2oM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>Now that I’ve been working with carbon credit data for a couple of years, it seems to me that the incumbent players like Verra have no incentive to make their data easily available and interoperable. While this data is ostensibly public, their terms of service are pretty vague about what constitutes appropriate use, and without the project data then claims about the underlying activity are impossible to verify. As the number of credit issuance systems increases, and interoperable public infrastructure like the KlimaDAO retirement aggregator are built to seamlessly integrate different types of credits, it is critically important that project and issuance data from the registries is made publicly available in an efficient and standardized manner.</p>
<p>In this talk, I basically invoke this xkcd comic to point out that we need a unified, open data standard for carbon credits:</p>
<p><a href="How Standards Proliferate">https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/standards.png</a></p>
<p>To flesh out my point, I lay out some of the limitations of the current registry-specific data models, reference some existing frameworks such as the UN SDGs and Planetary Boundaries, as well as point toward ongoing initiatives like the Ecological Benefits Frame Activator (of which I am a participant) and the <a href="https://climateactiondata.org/about/">Climate Action Data Trust</a> (in whose user forum KlimaDAO has applied to participate).</p>
<p>Finally, I provide an overview of the phased approach that KlimaDAO is taking to integrate carbon credit registry data given our need to ship products that work today, while preparing for a future where there are many more systems to integrate with and (hopefully) a standardized data model toward which to migrate.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-boston/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-boston/video-grab.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Boy Who Would Be Core</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/personal-journey/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero%27s_journey"><img src="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/personal-journey/https:/upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1b/Heroesjourney.svg/300px-Heroesjourney.svg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The Hero’s Journey</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Only those who do not seek power are qualified to hold it.” - Plato</p>
</blockquote>
<section id="greetings" class="level1">
<h1>Greetings</h1>
<p>As my pseudonym gives away, I’m a philosopher at heart. I find stoic teachings very relevant given the turbulent times we’re living through - though I’d hardly call myself a hardcore capital-S Stoic.</p>
</section>
<section id="impending-doom-great-expectations" class="level1">
<h1>Impending Doom; Great Expectations</h1>
<p>Growing up in Florida, the looming impact of rising sea levels and climate instability on the place where I grew up was evident to me from a young age.</p>
<p>My family always said they expected me to do something great, and I love learning, so school always came easily to me. But I had no idea how I would know what great labor I should take on, and though I thought climate action a worthy candidate, the path forward was not clear.</p>
<p>Later on, in college, I took a class on the Philosphical Problems of Climate Change. That course made it clear to me that ultimately climate change is a coordination game, but that incentives are not aligned for long term climate stability to in our status quo political and economic systems.</p>
<p>In particular, at least in the United States, politicians are only elected for 2-6 year terms - but climate change is a decadal process that requires long-term planning to manage. So for over a decade I felt powerless to contribute to the global coordination problem that is climate change - I’m too pragmatic for activism like protests and marches, but I’m not a typical engineer, and many sustainabiltiy companies I had looked at previously were looking for experience I didn’t have.</p>
</section>
<section id="humble-beginnings-in-academia" class="level1">
<h1>Humble Beginnings in Academia</h1>
<p>My academic background is in astrophysics and philosophy. I had the priveledge of doing research at Santa Fe Institute, where I connected with world-class transdisciplinary thinkers - and also realized the fundamental challenge I would face were I to continue in my academic career. Given the large number of PhDs being minted, and the small number of tenure-track positions available, the odds of success in academia struck me as quite unfavorable. Despite concerted effort to gain research experience during my undergrad to become a desirable PhD applicant, I did not succeed in publishing any papers before I graduated.</p>
<p>From my earliest exposure to philosophy, I’ve been very interested in epistemology - especially philosophy of science. How do scientific communities come to communal understanding of natural phenomena over time? How does that consensus understanding among experts come to be disseminated and integrated into the worldview of ordinary people?</p>
<p>So naturally when I began to pursue academic research of my own, I was drawn to verifying (or rather, in the spirit of Popper, falsifying) prominent theories in a particular niche. However, because I was comparing theoretical predictions with real-world data - and it turns out many theories in niche subfields have not been rigorously checked against data and often don’t stand up well - both my astro research and my research at SFI resulted in negative results.</p>
<p>My mentors and advisors always told me that negative results were not publishable, which I found immensely frustrating. How would other scientists know that this theory struggles to accurately model real data? Every researcher who tried to use this model to predict the behavior of real systems would find it doesn’t quite work, but without a paper rigorously documenting the inaccuracies that knowledge would never be integrated into the consensus understanding.</p>
<p>Still discouraged by these early experiences in academia, I’m keenly interested in the nascent DeSci space, as it may just offer solutions to some of academia’s problems, such as irreproducibility and gatekeeping by incumbent rent-seekers like journal publishers.</p>
</section>
<section id="learning-to-operate-in-organizations" class="level1">
<h1>Learning to Operate in Organizations</h1>
<p>Since school, I’ve been broadening out into an E-shaped person. Between the programming experience I picked up analyzing telescope images and working with genomic data in my research, combined with the critical thinking and problem solving skills from philosophy, made me very well suited to work in the emerging field of data science. I struggled a bit initially trying to get management consulting jobs with a data focus so I could work across a few different industries, but eventually I found a boutique data-focused consulting firm that would take me on.</p>
<p>Working inside of giant corporations as a consultant was a <em>highly</em> educating experience. While many view corporations as faceless, nameless behemoths that act with a unified heartless will, I rapidly understood how ossified and uncoordinated most corporations are internally, which explains how ordinary people “just trying to do their job” could be complicit in such horrendous decision-making.</p>
<p>After being pushed into management without insufficient resources and only 2 years of experience, it rapidly became clear to me I would not be able to grow and mature surrounded by people less experienced than me and led by men 30 years my senior who had no background in the technical work they were directing us to carry out.</p>
<p>So I left to find a software shop where my nascent data engineering and DevOps skillset would be nurtured and I could grow into a mature individual contributor in a technical organization. While I considered an offer from a crypto firm to lead the team building their infrastructure, this seemed like too much responsibility given my limited experience, so I settled into a mid-level software engineering job at a mid-stage AdTech startup building data pipelines and cloud infrastructure. The systems I built analyzed data from social media platforms to help advertisers make better decisions about what type of content to support with their ad spend, so they could avoid supporting content that might be harmful or damage their brand, as well as target content that would be likely to have viewers from their target audience.</p>
</section>
<section id="leaving-the-ordinary-world-behind" class="level1">
<h1>Leaving the Ordinary World Behind</h1>
<p>Back in 2016 or so I took a Coursera course about Bitcoin and distributed ledger technology, and it mentioned smart contracts briefly for insurance and real estate, but I didn’t see any of that actually being built at the time. Ethereum had just launched, and while it captured my imagination, it seemed more like a science fair project than a planetary-scale compute and settlement layer - so I remained a crypto-skeptic and moved on (for now).</p>
<p>In late 2020 I started learning more about crypto again at the behest of my neighbor - who had been participating in DeFi Summer. I fell down the rabbit hole, finally seeing real applications use smart contracts for basic financial use-cases like borrowing-and-lending (Aave) or decentralized swaps (Uniswap). I became a regular Bankless listener and started playing around with DeFi applications.</p>
<section id="entering-the-dark-forest" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="entering-the-dark-forest">Entering the Dark Forest</h2>
<p>It was just another Monday evening watching the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uM5XX4AwEuI">latest Bankless episode on YouTube</a>, but the more I heard the more I realized this was not just another crypto project. The idea of using blockchain technology to bring greater transparency and efficiency to climate finance struck me as a perfect combination of my experience with data and my longstanding desire to contribute my professional skills to support climate action.</p>
<p>Later that night I was pouring over the documentation and Discord, considering whether to put some of my own money at risk to support the project. This is what I’d been looking for: an opportunity to use my capital and skills to make a difference.</p>
<p>But things were not all sunny in paradise.</p>
<p>In the lead up to launch, there were many concerned and confused Klimates. I was quickly deputized as a moderator for my early work answering questions and helping people troubleshoot issues. The Core Team was busy and pulled in a million directions, so I did my best to keep the Discord under control, building Discord bots for Q/A and common metrics people were constantly asking for.</p>
<p>Launch was the most intense 48 hours of my life. We were on a voice chat for 16 hours straight, squashed bug after bug, and addressed hundreds of individual questions and issues. In the wake of the launch, there were suddenly hundreds of people who wanted to contribute to the DAO - utter chaos ensued, and I found myself called upon to lead.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-call-to-adventure" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-call-to-adventure">The Call to Adventure</h2>
<p>Around November or December, the Core Team first offered me to come aboard as a Core Contributor. At first I rejected the call to adventure, worried about the risk and instability of leaving my comfortable corporate AdTech data engineering gig to run my own company and provide services to a DAO.</p>
<p>But around the end of the year, my previous company got acquired at just the right moment to give me a little cash and a good reason to move on to a new adventure.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="documenting-my-journey" class="level1">
<h1>Documenting My Journey</h1>
<p>For the past year or so, my main gig has been Core Contributor at KlimaDAO, where I focus on data, strategy and governance. I’m also humbled to represent the DAO publicly by speaking at conferences, appearing on podcasts and speaking with media.</p>
<p>It’s been a joy to develop my public speaking skills sharing about a movement that I’m so passionate about, and begin my journey as a leader in the space as part of a community that I came up through organically, from a quiet observer in Discord, to a moderator, to building bots and dashboards, and finally stepping up to become a Core contributor.</p>
<p>After having several people ask me to document my journey and share insights I’ve gained along the way, I created this blog to serve as a public journal.</p>
<p>While I will carefully maintain the consistency of which identity is tied to which project, I will use this blog as a place to make observations from my unique perspective as a whole person - which may occassionally blur the line between my personas. More on my thoughts about pseudonymity and identity to come.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>journey</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/personal-journey/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Novel Demand Generation Talk @ Sustainable Blockchain Summit 2022 in Bogota</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-bogota-demand/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1tiVJbbiVf0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>This short talk highlights a structural problem in the traditional carbon market, where the infrequent but large purchases from corporate end-users of carbon credits leads to very “chunky” demand. In turn, holders of carbon credits become very defensive about their inventory and price data, leading to opacity, fragmentation and lack of liquidity.</p>
<p>To address this issue, I highlight novel demand sources being developed by KlimaDAO, from automated retirements on DeFi applications like Sushi to compensating for emissions from live events, or even integrating carbon credits into social media applications.</p>
<p>At the event, this talk was the seed for a breakout session, where I moderated a lively discussion about potential demand sources that could address the chunky demand problem. One of the most interesting ideas to come out of that discussion was to offer carbon credit retirement as an optional benefit to employees via a payroll provider like TriNet or ADP - and now I’m trying to develop a partnership with a small crypto-forward payroll provider to try something like that out!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-bogota-demand/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/sbs-bogota-demand/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building the Next Generation of Market-Based Climate Action @ Thought For Food NYC 2022</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/thought-for-food-nyc-22/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/791229811?h=7cca8b7842" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>
<a href="https://vimeo.com/791229811">Marcus Aurelius at TFF Generation Fest 2022</a> from <a href="https://vimeo.com/thoughtforfoodorg">Thought For Food</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.
</p>
<p>It was truly a pleasure to speak at and help offset the carbon emissions associated with Thought For Food’s fantastic annual event in New York City. True to their innovative nature, we conducted a live offsetting demo that gave our team valueable insights about how best to integrate carbon credit retirement into live events.</p>
<p>Of course the food at the event was amazing, and I really appreciated the TFF team’s commitment to mitigate emissions where possible and offset any residual emissions. Making this the norm for live events will be a critical driver of novel, consistent demand for consuming ecological benefit assets like carbon credits.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>presentations</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/thought-for-food-nyc-22/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/thought-for-food-nyc-22/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="72" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ponzinomics Debate @ DeFiDay 2022 in Amsterdam</title>
  <dc:creator>Marcus Aurelius</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/defiday-22-ponzinomics/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<iframe width="800" height="500" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Gme_vKcIVkU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>I had a blast engaging in spirited debate with Seraphim (Euler Finance) and Frank (Oasis), two thoughtful and innovative DeFi builders.</p>
<p>While Frank was framed as the antagonist, advocating that Ponzinomics are an inherently unsustainable mechanism, I clearly articulated my position that Ponzinomics can be useful for incentivizing early adoption, but is not a value proposition in and of itself.</p>
<p>The key difference that turns a project utilizing Ponzinomics to incentivize early adopters into a Ponzi scheme is the lack of a clear path to generating real value for real users. As long as there is a legitimate value proposition to the products or services provided by the project, it’s not appropriate to accuse that project of being a Ponzi scheme.</p>
<p>I love this debate format for panels, it’s much more engaging for both panelists and the audience when there are principled disagreements and spicy takes playing out live on-stage. I hope more event organizers learn from the wonderful team at <a href="https://www.cryptocanal.org/">CryptoCanal</a>, and go beyond crowded generic panels where the moderator just goes down the line asking stock questions.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <category>panels</category>
  <category>klimadao</category>
  <guid>https://www.marcus.limo/posts/defiday-22-ponzinomics/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.marcus.limo/posts/defiday-22-ponzinomics/video-grab.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="73" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
